A Guide to the Gay, Lesbian, and Straight Education Network (GLSEN), Richmond Chapter Archives, 2000-2005
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
Gay, Lesbian, and Straight Education Network (GLSEN), Richmond Chapter Archives 2000-2005
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
M324
1.44 linear feet
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Box 4 restricted until September 12, 2003
Acquisition Information
On September 12, 2003, John Leppo, Co-chair of the GLSEN Richmond Chapter, donated materials to Special Collections and Archives at James Branch Cabell library. Additional materials were donated by John Leppo on January 20, 2005.
Biographical/Historical Information
GLSEN (The Gay, Lesbian, and Straight Education Network) is a national organization fighting to end anti-gay bias in primary and secondary schools. The Richmond, Virginia chapter first met in January 2000 and received official chapter accreditation in July 2001. The chapter's long-term goal is to "end sexual orientation and gender identity bias in Richmond City, Henrico County, Chesterfield County, and Hanover County schools." As of January 2003, GLSEN Richmond included fifty-two members and a mailing list of one hundred and fifty addresses. GLSEN Richmond is a founding member of the Safe Schools Richmond Coalition, a coalition of community organizations working for the inclusion of sexual orientation and gender identity under the anti-harassment policies of area school systems. GLSEN also helps local students form GSAs (Gay Straight Alliances) in their schools to promote a "safe and respectful environment for all members of the school regardless of sexual orientation and gender identity." GLSEN sponsors GSA leadership summits twice a year to develop youth leaders and to bolster club activities. GLSEN offers a small grants program to help finance GSA activities, provide resources, and to facilitate the Richmond GSA list-serv. Other areas of focus include public education to increase awareness of the needs of LGBT youth, developing resources and a program to provide support and information to LGBT faculty and staff, and providing curriculum development grants for faculty interested in incorporating sexual orientation and gender identity into their curriculum.
Scope and Content
The collection includes meeting minutes, various organizational records, publications, articles, outreach materials, and multi-media.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically and chronologically therein. Box 1 and 2 contain the bulk of the collection. Box 3 includes a video and a bound copy of the 2003 Chapter Leadership and Board of Directors Handbook. Box 4 contains restricted material to be made available on September 13, 2013.
Contents List
- Documents and Publications, 2000-2005 (Box 1, Folder 1-35)
  Contains correspondence, meeting minutes, publications, and outreach materials.
  alphabetical
  - Accreditation, 2002-2003 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Accreditation Application, 2004-2005 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Annual Business Meeting Minutes, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Annual Chapter Budget, 2004-2005 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Articles, 2002-2004 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Board of Directors Meetings, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Chapter Leadership and Board of Directors Handbook, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Chapter Meeting Minutes, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Chapter Meeting Minutes, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Chapter Meeting Minutes, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Chapter Meeting Minutes, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Chapter Meeting Minutes, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Community Needs Assessment Project, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Financial Report, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Membership, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - National Day of Silence, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - The Newsletter (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Publications (GLSEN National), 2000-2002 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Publications (GLSEN Richmond), c. 2002-2003 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Richmond Area Gay Straight Alliance, Jump Start Resources, 2001-2002 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Richmond Area Gay Straight Alliance, Resource CD, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Richmond Area Gay Straight Alliance, Resource Handbook, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Richmond Area Gay Straight Alliance Summit (First), 2002 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Richmond Area Gay Straight Alliance Summit (Second), 2003 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Richmond Area Gay Straight Alliance Summit (Fourth), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Richmond Area Gay Straight Alliance Summit (Fifth), 2004 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Safe Schools Coalition, Henrico County Public Schools, 2004-2005 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Safe Schools Coalition Media Press Kit, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Safe Schools Coalition Meetings, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Safe Schools Coalition Publications, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Safe Schools Coalition Resource Packet, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Items with Miscellaneous Formats, 2003 (Box 3)
  - Safe Schools Coalition Summit, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Strategic Plans and Goals, 2004-2005 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- Items with miscellaneous formats, 2003 (Box 3)
  - Leadership and Board of Directors Handbook, 2003 (Box 3)
  - Safe Schools Campaign Television Ad. Aired on MTV (Music Telvision) and BET (Black Entertainment Television), 2003 (Box 3)
- Restricted Materials, 2000-2003 (Box 4, Folder 1-5)
  - Board of Directors Meetings, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Chapter Meeting Minutes, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Chapter Meeting Minutes, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Chapter Meeting Minutes, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Chapter Meeting Minutes, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Board of Directors Meetings, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 1)